Joaquin Peña Fernández

joapen@gmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/jpenafernand

https://joapen.com

Location = Philadelphia (PA)

Willing to travel, European citizen and US Green Card holder (I take care of my visa).

Senior Program Manager

Motivation

Client focused and result oriented professional with deep expertise in Corporate Strategy, Mapping frameworks, large scale Technology Program and Portfolio Management and Excellence in Execution.

I am looking to put into practice my expertise in program, delivery management and experience in technology.

The way I like to work is:

- Understand the client expectation: what they really need, what they aspire to have, what they would love to have.
- Vision and communicate where we want to go, tell the team how we are going to do it together.
- Inspire confidence about the plans we have, the fact we can do it, and we will be able to solve the problems that will show up.
- Understand the environment and the way people are working within other functional teams, so I can have perspective and make good decisions.
- Understand how the numbers are progressing, what factors are driving the change, and what can be done to improve results.
- Not attached to my own ideas, but I ask a lot because I just want the best idea to win.
- Able to go deep into technical discussions.

The values I subscribe to and type of organization that I want to work for: an organization that enable its employees the autonomy to work with integrity to deliver the value to the customer.

By personal reasons we just moved in from Spain to Philadelphia.

Frameworks: PMI, Scrum, Kanban, ITIL, Six Sigma, CMMI, COBIT, SAFE, LUMA, Wardley Maps, Theory of Constraints.

Industry experience: manufacturing, aerospace, consumer & retail, finance, telecom, transport and public sector.

Functional expertise: Finance, HHRR, compliance, supply chain, quality, shop floor engineering.

Languages: English (full professional), Spanish (native), French (medium), German (elementary).

Experience

01/2021 - Today Founder & Director (Company : Mapas)

- Authored the book, <u>Draw your company strategy</u> published in English and <u>Spanish</u>.
- Competitive analysis of companies, describing the actual landscape, anticipation of potential gameplays, and foresight of different scenarios.
- Drive the definition of strategic playbooks and complete their execution.
- Improved the quality and clearness of strategic plans through reviews and identification of areas for improvement, which is valuable feedback for executive leads.
- Analysis of IT architecture and design with recommendations of improvement for adapting the IT landscape to the business challenges.

- Provided guidance, concrete tools and mechanisms to execution teams to increase their strategic attitude towards uncertainty.
- Speaker on Business Strategy & Mapping Frameworks.
- Creator of the course Acelera tu Aprendizaje en Mapas de Wardley.
- Conducting research to identify new economic patterns in the manufacturing industry using data driven and strategy mapping tools).
- Event sponsor at https://wardleymapsforbusiness.com/

01/2022 - Today Senior Principal Program Manager @ DXC Technology

Re-enter the work after the leave of absence.

01/2020 - 12/2021 Personal Leave of absense

During my time away from work to focus on the care of a sick (and now healthy) child I was able to nourish my desire to learn and develop professionally in the following ways:

- Studied: Machine learning applied to the financial markets, using different time series techniques and neural networks (python, Jupyter...).
- Authored the book <u>DREAM</u>, a practical model and repeatable framework for learning how to invest in the financial markets.

04/2017 – 12/2019 Senior principal Program Manager @ DXC Technology

- Define the offerings of large-scale transition and transformation programs (25M\$-150M\$).
- Define, build, and manage large multidisciplinary global teams to execute the programs.
- Lead teams of project managers to successfully deliver their projects. Oversee the program implementations and the P&L.
- Have the client and the internal stakeholders updated and engaged with the progress of the program initiatives.
- Focus on change management at business level and IT level.
- Frequently asked to take over complex accounts that required Rapid intervention activities.
- Able to adapt quickly to customers of different industries. I have worked on: Aerospace, Telecommunications, Public sector, Manufacturing, Transport.

04/2014 – 03/2017 Senior Principal Engagement Manager @ Computer Science Corporation

- Geographic area covered by the portfolio: Spain and Portugal.
- Manage the firm's cross industry technology portfolio for the Iberia region with a focus on ensuring governance and profitability of the client engagements.
- Guide the 5 teams of industry specific delivery managers: Industries: Manufacturing, Pharma, Insurance, Public sector, & Telecommunications.
- Manager for 9 direct reports of leaders in each industry group.
- P&L ownership of the portfolio (\$15m \$16m).
- Continued delivering the Applications Services for DuPont EMEA.
- Engagement summary: SAP Governance program for payments in Catalunya, Ariba e-procurement system for Talgo, Principado de Asturias PMO, Ariba e-procurement service for Telefonica, R&D Document Management for Almirall, consulting services for Hotelbeds, SalesForce implementations for Mapfre, SAP taxes system for Govern D'Andorra.

01/2010 – 03/2014 Principal Consultant Delivery Manager @ Computer Science Corporation Two main assignments during this period at the same time.

DuPont EMEA Applications Delivery Manager (01/2010 – 12/2019)

- Responsible for the DuPont and Axalta Coating Systems (\$10m/year) applications portfolio.
- Managed a multinational team of project and service managers (7 9 direct reports).
- Portfolio management, service delivery management and contract management.
- Business development and sales of new projects/services for a total of 4m\$/year.
- Increase the direct cost margins of the portfolio every single year.
- Engagement summary: DPC Reach Management Database (.NET; 500k\$), Safety Reports Generation on MS-SharePoint (Seveso II, 650k\$), SAP HR Improvement initiative (Lean Six Sigma, 250k\$), SAP HCM Technical Upgrade (900k\$, Panaya), SAP HCM Clone (780k\$, SAP Landscape Transformation), Finance asset allocation forecast solution, MS .Net Rebates solution for EMEA, e-Logistics call center Service for EMEA, Marketing data readiness Project for EMEA, DTF quality and manufacturing applications support, DPC MES tools, Chemours split program, Corteva split program, PBX support for 8 centers, HR Dow personnel integration project,

SAP Basis support for services and projects in EMEA.

Engagement Manager for Airbus Spain (10/2012 - 3/2014)

- Structure & lead the transition of a global contract from the previous service provider to CSC.
- Grow the account by identifying new opportunities & closing those deals for additional value of 600k\$ in just 8 months.

Engagement summary: SPRINT Automation of Design effectivity calculations (260k\$).

01/2008 – 12/2009 Project Office Manager (PMO Lead) @ Computer Science Corporation

- Coordinate operations and create best practice and process standardizations for all the PMOs across global accounts.
- Coaching & mentoring for a team of 28 program and project managers: Asturias Government PMO, Delphi Infrastructure PMO, DuPont PMO, UTC Infrastructure PMO for EMEA.
- Prepare offerings of 3m\$ to 25m\$. Produce sales documentation for "PMO solution".
- Implementation of delivery assurance process in Spain.
- Lead specific cost improvement initiatives under Lean Six Sigma.
- · Coach on Scrum implementations.

01/2007 – 12/2007 EMEA Applications Service Manager @ Computer Science Corporation

- Lead the applications service support team for DuPont EMEA.
- Manage a team of 7 people.
- Coach mentor and motivate team.
- Establish a good work atmosphere. Lead and model a customer centric approach.
- Identify new business opportunities & technology solutions that address additional client needs.
- Ensure compliance with contractual commitments related to quality, cost, and schedule.
- Risk assessment and development of risk mitigation plans.
- Create a scoreboard to inform and evaluate the service.
- Engagement summary: Delegation of Authority App for EMEA (finance), document management system for manufacturing processes for each plant (12 instances), HHRR employee complaint solution, Reach compliance solution for tracking suppliers data.

01/2005 – 12/2006 Proposal & Project Manager @ Abengoa (Telvent Division)

- Prepare offers and then execute those projects (volume of 600k€/year) for different business units throughout Abengoa.
- Completion of SLDC projects under budget, meeting the schedule and staying on scope.
- Manage a team of 10 people.
- Responsible for hiring of for contracting labor outsourcing to adjust for volume of work.
- Engagement summary: Purchasing solution, Warehouse & Shipment, Financial compliance, Financing and Accounting, Proposal Management, Strategic investments, Legal and Workflow Management, GRC authorization solution.
- Frameworks used: Waterfall and Kanban.

01/2003 – 12/2004 Product Manager @ Abengoa (Telvent Division)

- Functional analysis: Gather functional requirements and build the technical analysis and design dossier. Obtain the sign-off of these documents.
- Implementation of a software development procedure for developers (nomenclature, best practices), accelerating the work completed and the quality of the deliverables.
- Define the architecture of complex and distributed web Apps (construction of common JavaScript libraries for the development team).
- Engagement summary: Proposal Management implementation (replicated in 85 servers), Strategic investments solution, helpdesk web application, support of the GRC solution, travel management solution (web based, 15 instances), holidays authorization tool (+50 instances).

04/2001 – 12/2002 Application Developer @ Abengoa (Abentel Division)

- Software development, technical design, testing and deployment activities for web-based solutions in Lotus Notes. Testing web applications with semi-automated tools.
- Engagement summary: Providers evaluation web solution, management of tools between plants, ticketing system for field services.

 Technical design, development, testing, deployment and maintenance of applications in Lotus Notes with web based front end (html, CSS and JavaScript). Work as Lotus Domino Administrator. • Engagement summary: creation of the intranet webs for the pay (5 intranets).

Education

Bachelor's degree Electronics Engineering, University of Cadiz.

Certifications

TITLES	DATE
DevOps Dojo White Belt	July 2018
Project Management Professional (PMP) (ID# = 4856789)	August 2017
Six Sigma Lean/DFSS Black Belt	January 2015
Scrum Fundamentals (ID: 67674)	October 2014
COBIT 5 Foundation (ID#: 02867429-2-424P)	May 2014
ITIL V3 Foundation	January 2012
Lotus Designer CLP	2007, 2005

(End of the document)